哈尔滨工业大学 IBM技术中心
倾情制作
计算机程序的构造和解释
字幕&时间轴
邓雄飞
(Dysprosium)
后期&特效
蔡钟毓
(JohnTitor)
校对
匿名
特别感谢
裘宗燕教授
I'd like to welcome you to this course on computer science.
欢迎大家来一起学习这门计算机科学的基础课程
Actually, that's a terrible way to start.
事实上 以这样的方式来表述并不恰当
Computer science is a terrible name for this business.
于此来说 计算机科学是个糟糕的名字
First of all, it's not a science.
首先 它不算是一门科学
It might be engineering or it might be art,
它更应该被称为工程或者是艺术
but we'll actually see that computer so-called science
但我们实际上会发现 这个所谓的计算机科学
actually has a lot in common with magic,
却与魔法一样的有众多神奇之处
and we'll see that in this course.
这些将会在课程中一一体现
So it's not a science.
所以 不能称其为一门科学
It's also not really very much about computers.
这门学科和“计算机”也并非紧密相关
And it's not about computers in the same sense
类似的 就像我们说
that physics is not really about particle accelerators,
物理学中并不仅仅有关粒子加速器
and biology is not really about microscopes and petri dishes.
生物学中并不全然是显微镜和培养皿一样
And it's not about computers in the same sense
同理
that geometry is not really about using surveying instruments.
几何学中也并不全是介绍如何使用测量仪器
In fact, there's a lot of commonality
事实上 计算机科学和几何学
between computer science and geometry.
有很多共性
Geometry, first of all,
首先 几何学
is another subject with a lousy name.
只是另一个有个糟糕名字的学科
The name comes from Gaia, meaning the Earth,
这个名字来自于Gaia 意为土地
and metron, meaning to measure.
以及metron 意为测量
Geometry originally meant measuring the Earth or surveying.
几何学最初意为测地或者勘探
And the reason for that was that, thousands of years ago,
这是因为数千年前的埃及祭司
the Egyptian priesthood developed the rudiments of geometry
为了计算如何去修复年年被尼罗河的洪水
in order to figure out how to restore the boundaries of fields
所毁坏的牧田边界
that were destroyed in the annual flooding of the Nile.
而建立了几何学基础
And to the Egyptians who did that,
而对出于这个目的的埃及人来说
geometry really was the use of surveying instruments.
几何学的确是掌握对测量仪器的使用
Now, the reason that we think computer science is about computers
现在 我们以为计算机科学就是介绍计算机的使用
is pretty much the same reason that the Egyptians thought geometry
就正如埃及人认为
was about surveying instruments.
几何学是介绍如何使用测量仪器的
And that is, when some field is just getting started
换句话说 任何一门学科起步的时候
and you don't really understand it very well,
你都对它了解不深
it's very easy to confuse the essence of what you're doing with the tools that you use.
这很容易使你混淆所做的事与所用之物
And indeed, on some absolute scale of things,
确实 就绝对规模来说
we probably know less about the essence of computer science
我们对计算机科学的实质的了解
than the ancient Egyptians really knew about geometry.
比埃及人对几何学的了解还少
Well, what do I mean by the essence of computer science?
那么 我所谓的计算机科学的本质是什么呢
What do I mean by the essence of geometry?
我所谓的几何学本质又是什么呢
See, it's certainly true that these Egyptians went off
看 可以确认的是 古埃及人确实使用测量仪器
and used surveying instruments,
并且已经消失多年
but when we look back on them after a couple of thousand years,
但当我们在几千年后回过头来重新审视这段历史
we say,
我们会说
gee, what they were doing,
天啊 看他们在做什么
the important stuff they were doing,
他们的工作是多么的重要
was to begin to formalize notions about space and time,
已经开始对时间和空间进行形式化表述
to start a way of talking about mathematical truths formally.
并归纳出一套讨论数学真理的形式化方法
That led to the axiomatic method.
这直接导致了公理化方法
That led to sort of all of modern mathematics,
以及各种现代数学的产生
figuring out a way to talk precisely about
同时也指明了一种精确讨论
so-called declarative knowledge, what is true.
所谓的描述真理的陈述性知识的方法
Well, similarly, I think in the future people will look back and say,
与此相似的 我认为未来人们会回过头来审视并说
yes, those primitives in the 20th century were fiddling around
啊 这些20世纪的原始人
with these gadgets called computers,
不务正业地玩弄着叫计算机的小玩意
but really what they were doing is starting to learn
但它们真正在做的是开始学习
how to formalize intuitions about process,
如何去对计算过程进行形式化表述
how to do things,
如何去解决问题
starting to develop a way to talk precisely about how-to knowledge,
并结合两者发展一套对问题处理过程精确表述的方法
as opposed to geometry that talks about what is true.
这与讨论真理的几何学形成了对照
Let me give you an example of that.
让我给你们举个例子吧
Let's take a look
来瞧瞧
Here is a piece of mathematics that says what a square root is.
数学中是这样来定义平方根的:
The square root of X is the number Y,
定义X的平方根Y是这样一个数
such that Y squared is equal to X and Y is greater than 0.
Y的平方等于X 且Y大于等于0
Now, that's a fine piece of mathematics,
这是一个很好的定义
but just telling you what a square root is
但它只告诉了你平方根是什么
doesn't really say anything about how you might go out and find one.
却没有告诉你如何去求取一个平方根
So let's contrast that with a piece of imperative knowledge,
那么我们将其与一条指令性知识做比较
how you might go out and find a square root.
你如何去求取一个平方根
This, in fact, also comes from Egypt, not ancient, ancient Egypt.
事实上 这来自于埃及 不太久远的埃及
This is an algorithm due to Heron of Alexandria,
亚历山大的Heron提出的一个算法
called how to find a square root by successive averaging.
称作连续取均值求平方根法
And what it says is that,
这个算法是说
in order to find a square root,
为了算出平方根
you make a guess, you improve that guess --
首先你应该给出一个猜测值guess 并不断改进
and the way you improve the guess
改进的方法是通过
is to average the guess and X over the guess,
不断求猜测值guess与X/guess的平均值
and we'll talk a little bit later about
我们稍后将会讨论
why that's a reasonable thing--
为什么这是合理的
and you keep improving the guess until it's good enough.
通过不断改进 直到它足够精确
That's a method.
这就是实现方法
That's how to do something as opposed to
这也是如何完成一项工作与
declarative knowledge that says what you're looking for.
其对应的陈述性知识的对照
That's a process.
这就是一个过程
Well, what's a process in general?
那么 通常来说什么是过程呢？
It's kind of hard to say.
这定义起来非常困难
You can think of it as like a magical spirit
你可以将它象征性地看成一个活在计算机内
that sort of lives in the computer and does something.
并且可以完成一些操作的精灵
And the thing that directs a process is
一些被称为程序的规则模式
a pattern of rules called a procedure.
指导着这类过程的进行
So procedures are the spells, if you like,
程序可以被认为是符咒
that control these magical spirits that are the processes.
使用程序来控制这些精灵完成一些操作就叫做过程
I guess you know everyone needs a magical language,
你们知道人人都需要一门魔法语言
and sorcerers, real sorcerers,
那些魔术师 真正的魔术师 用远古的阿卡狄亚语
use ancient Arcadian or Sumerian or Babylonian or whatever.
或者苏美尔语 或者巴比伦语 或者其它的
We're going to conjure our spirits
而我们将用一门叫Lisp的魔法语言
in a magical language called Lisp,
来召唤出我们的精灵
which is a language designed for talking about,
这门语言是被设计用来
for casting the spells that are procedures to direct the processes.
编写如咒语版的程序 来指导过程的进行
Now, it's very easy to learn Lisp.
学习Lisp非常容易
In fact, in a few minutes, I'm going to teach you,
事实上 我会在几分钟内教会你
essentially, all of Lisp.
整个Lisp
I'm going to teach you, essentially, all of the rules.
及其所有的规则
And you shouldn't find that particularly surprising.
你不必感到很惊讶
That's sort of like saying it's very easy
这就像你在学习象棋时
to learn the rules of chess.
认为象棋的规则十分简单一样
And indeed, in a few minutes,
事实也如此 几分钟内
you can tell somebody the rules of chess.
你可以与任何人谈论象棋的规则
But of course, that's very different from
但是 这全然不等同于说
saying you understand the implications of those rules
你所知道这些规则所蕴含的东西
and how to use those rules to become a masterful chess player.
以及如何利用这些规则去成为象棋大师
Well, Lisp is the same way.
Lisp也是如此
We're going to state the rules in a few minutes,
我将在几分钟内道清规则
and it'll be very easy to see.
这说起来非常容易
But what's really hard is going to be the implications of those rules,
但真正困难的是如何运用这些规则
how you exploit those rules to be a master programmer.
以及你如何利用这些规则成为编程大师
And the implications of those rules are going to take us the,
这些规则的应用将占据我们
well, the whole rest of the subject and, of course, way beyond.
余下的课程 甚至更多
OK, so in computer science,
所以 在计算机科学中
we're in the business of
我们的任务则是
formalizing this sort of how-to imperative knowledge,
形式化这种如有关“怎么做”的指令性知识
how to do stuff.
并将之付诸实际
And the real issues of computer science are, of course,
这也便是计算机科学的真正的议题
not telling people how to do square roots.
当然 并不是告诉人们如何去求平方根
Because if that was all it was,
因为如果那是计算机科学的全部的的话
there wouldn't be no big deal.
就不会有什么大问题了
The real problems come when we try to
真正的问题来自于当我们尝试
build very, very large systems,
构建非常非常大的系统时
computer programs that are thousands of pages long,
程序可能会长达数千页
so long that nobody can really hold them in their heads all at once.
长得没有人能马上将其装入脑中
And the only reason that that's possible is because
而使这些得以实现则是因为
there are techniques for controlling the complexity of these large systems.
我们有在大系统中控制复杂度的技术
And these techniques that are controlling complexity
这些控制复杂度的技术
are what this course is really about.
正是我们课程所讨论的
And in some sense,
从某种意义上来说
that's really what computer science is about.
这也正是计算机科学的关键所在
Now, that may seem like a very strange thing to say.
这样说听起来或许很奇怪
Because after all, a lot of people besides computer scientists
毕竟 除了计算机科学家外
deal with controlling complexity.
仍然有很多人在做复杂度控制相关的工作
A large airliner is an extremely complex system,
一个航班就是一个非常复杂的系统
and the aeronautical engineers who design that
设计它的航空工程师
are dealing with immense complexity.
便在处理这个巨大的复杂度
But there's a difference between that kind of complexity
但这种复杂度又与
and what we deal with in computer science.
计算机科学中的（复杂度）有别
And that is that computer science,
从某种意义上来说
in some sense, isn't real.
因为计算机科学不是“现实”的
You see, when an engineer is designing a physical system,
例如 当一名工程师设计物理系统时
that's made out of real parts.
这些都是由实在的物理部件构成
The engineers who worry about that
负责的该工作的工程师
have to address problems of tolerance and approximation and noise in the system.
就得对付系统中的公差、近似值以及噪声
So for example, as an electrical engineer,
譬如说 作为一名电气工程师
I can go off and easily build a one-stage amplifier
可以很容易的做一个单极放大器
or a two-stage amplifier,
或者是一个双极放大器
and I can imagine cascading a lot of them
也可想象将其大量串联
to build a million-stage amplifier.
来建造一个百万极的放大器
But it's ridiculous to build such a thing,
但这样做是不可行的
because long before the millionth stage,
因为在远没到百万数量级的时候
the thermal noise in those components way at the beginning
这种组合方法打从头产生的热噪声
is going to get amplified and make the whole thing meaningless.
会慢慢增强 并使得我们的幸苦付之一炬
Computer science deals with idealized components.
计算机科学处理的是理想化组件
We know as much as we want about these little program
我们对将要结合在一起的
and data pieces that we're fitting things together.
程序和数据了如指掌
We don't have to worry about tolerance.
我们不需要去关心公差
And that means that, in building a large program,
也就是说 在构建大系统时
there's not all that much difference
在我理想和现实之间
between what I can build and what I can imagine,
并不没有太大的不同
because the parts are these abstract entities
因为这些部分都是抽象单元
that I know as much as I want.
可以随心所欲的组合
I know about them as precisely as I'd like.
可以据目前所知而自由构建
So as opposed to other kinds of engineering,
就是与其它的工程不同之处
where the constraints on what you can build
（在其它的工程中）对你所构建系统的约束
are the constraints of physical systems,
来自于物理系统以及
the constraints of physics and noise and approximation,
物理定律 噪声 近似值等
the constraints imposed in building large software systems
而建立大型软件系统时所施加的约束
are the limitations of our own minds.
就是对我们大脑的限制
So in that sense,
从这个角度来看
computer science is like an abstract form of engineering.
计算机科学就像是工程中的一种抽象形式
It's the kind of engineering where you ignore
在这种工程中 我们忽略
the constraints that are imposed by reality.
现实所施加的约束
Well, what are some of these techniques?
那么 这其中有哪些技术呢
They're not special to computer science.
计算机科学中并没有特别的技术
First technique, which is used in all of engineering,
第一个技术是在很多工程中都使用的
is a kind of abstraction called black-box abstraction.
被称为“黑盒抽象”的方法
Take something and build a box about it.
即将一些东西组合并封装起来
Let's see, for example, if we looked at that square root method,
以之前我们提到的求取平方根的方法为例
I might want to take that and build a box.
我将这些操作视为一个“盒子”
That sort of says, to find the square root of X.
也就是说 为了找到X的平方根
And that might be a whole complicated set of rules.
或许会有一系列的复杂规则
And that might end up being a kind of thing where I can put in,
我们将规则封装 输入数据即可获得结果
say, 36 and say, what's the square root of 36?
比如说 输入36 然后说36的平方根是多少呢
And out comes 6.
则给出结果 6
And the important thing is that
重点是
I'd like to design that so that
通过这样的设计
if George comes along and would like to compute,
可以方便他人的使用
say, the square root of A plus the square root of B,
例如Goerge想计算A的平方根加上B的平方根
he can take this thing and use it as a module
他无需了解“盒子”内部的构成
without having to look inside
而直接可以以模块的形式使用它
and build something that looks like this,
也可以利用它去构建新的“盒子”
like an A and a B and a square root box and another square root box
例如构建一个 A和B以及一个平方根和或者另一个平方根盒子
and then something that adds that would put out the answer.
然后将这些结果加在一起并输出答案
And you can see, just from the fact that I want to do that,
如你所见 就我想实现的功能的层面来看
is from George's point of view,
对于George来说
the internals of what's in here should not be important.
盒子内部是什么样并不重要
So for instance, it shouldn't matter that, when I wrote this,
例如 以下这些说法都没什么问题
I said I want to find the square root of X.
我说求X的平方根
I could have said the square root of Y,
也可以说计算Y的平方根
or the square root of A, or anything at all
或者其它任何数的平方根
That's the fundamental notion of putting something in a box
黑盒抽象的基本规则是
using black-box abstraction to suppress detail.
将处理过程放入盒子里以隐藏细节
And the reason for that is you want to go off and build bigger boxes.
这样做的原因则是你可以脱身去构建更大的盒子
Now, there's another reason for doing black-box abstraction
现在 除了隐藏细节外
other than you want to suppress detail for building bigger boxes.
使用黑盒抽象还有另外一个原因
Sometimes you want to say that your way of doing something,
有的时候 你想要用你的方法去完成一件事
your how-to method,
你的方法
is an instance of a more general thing,
就是一个通法的具体实例
and you'd like your language to be able to express that generality.
同时 你也希望你的表述方式能够具有普遍性
Let me show you another example
我们接着用实例来说明
sticking with square roots.
继续刚才关于平方根的讨论
Let's go back and take another look at that slide
让我们回过头再来看看
with the square root algorithm on it.
求平方根的算法
Remember what that says.
想一想之前是怎么说的
That says, in order to do something, I make a guess,
为了求解 首先要作出猜测
and I improve that guess, and I sort of keep improving that guess.
然后基于这个猜测 做出持续不断的改进
So there's the general strategy of, I'm looking for something,
因此就存在一个找到某个到结果的通用方法
and the way I find it is that I keep improving it.
就是持续不断地改进结果
Now, that's a particular case of another kind of strategy
求取不动点的方法有很多
for finding a fixed point of something.
这种方法只是其中的一个特例
So you have a fixed point of a function.
每个函数都有一个不动点
A fixed point of a function is something, is a value.
函数的不动点是一个值
A fixed point of a function F is a value Y, such that F of Y equals Y.
F的不动点Y满足F(Y)=Y
And the way I might do that is start with a guess.
首先要做是做出一个猜测
And then if I want something that doesn't change when I keep applying F,
在迭代函数F时不会改变的东西则是我们所求的结果
is I'll keep applying F over and over until that result doesn't change very much.
我会不断迭代函数F直到结果不会有很大改变
So there's a general strategy.
这就是一个通法
And then, for example, to compute the square root of X,
因此 为了计算X的平方根
I can try and find a fixed point of the function which takes Y to the average of X/Y.
我可以试着找到Y与X/Y的平均值函数的不动点
And the idea that is that if I really had Y equal to the square root of X,
因为如果我真有一个等于X平方根的Y
then Y and X/Y would be the same value.
那么Y和X/Y应为同一值
They'd both be the square root of X,
它们俩都是X的平方根
because X over the square root of X is the square root of X.
因为X除根号X得根号X
And so the average if Y were equal to the square of X,
如果平均值Y等于X的平方根
then the average wouldn't change.
那么这个平均值就不会改变
So the square root of X is a fixed point of that particular function.
因此X的平方根即是某一特定函数的不动点
Now, what I'd like to have, I'd like to express
现在 我将要描述
the general strategy for finding fixed points.
寻找不动点的通法
So what I might imagine doing, is to find,
我所希望做的就是
is to be able to use my language to define a box that says "fixed point,"
用我自己的语言定义一个可以获得不动点的“盒子”
just like I could make a box that says "square root."
正如我可以定义一个输出平方根的盒子一样
And I'd like to be able to express this in my language.
我想要用自己的语言来表述
So I'd like to express not only the imperative how-to knowledge
因此 对于这种“怎么做”的指令性知识
of a particular thing like square root,
我不仅是想表达具体应该如何求平方根
but I'd like to be able to express the imperative knowledge
我也希望能够表述更加通用问题
of how to do a general thing like how to find fixed point.
例如 怎么求取不动点
And in fact, let's go back and look at that slide again.
让我们再回过头来看看之前的幻灯片
See, not only is this a piece of imperative knowledge,
不但如何去求取一个不动点
how to find a fixed point,
是一种指令性知识
but over here on the bottom,
在这下面 这里
there's another piece of imperative knowledge which says,
这儿还有另一种指令性知识 说的是
one way to compute square root is to apply this general fixed point method.
计算平方根的一种方法就是应用找不动点的方法
So I'd like to also be able to express that imperative knowledge.
如果 也想要表述这种指令性知识
What would that look like?
那结果会是什么样呢？
That would say, this fixed point box is such that
这个不动点盒子可能会是这样
if I input to it the function that takes Y to the average of Y and X/Y,
如果我输入一个函数 该函数从Y映射到Y和X/Y的平均值
then what should come out of that fixed point box is a method for finding square roots.
然后我们将会得到求不动点的盒子就是求平方根的一个方法
So in these boxes we're building,
因此在这些我们构建的盒子中
we're not only building boxes that you input numbers and output numbers,
输入和输出都不局限于数字
we're going to be building in boxes that,
我们将要构建能够
in effect, compute methods like finding square root.
找到平方根计算方法的盒子
And my take is their inputs functions,
我输入的是一个函数
like Y goes to the average of Y and X/Y.
比如Y映射到Y和X/Y的平均值的函数
The reason we want to do that,
我们之所以采用这种方式是希望
the reason this is a procedure, will end up being a procedure,
输入是一个过程 输出也是一个过程
as we'll see, whose value is another procedure,
如我们所见 一个过程输出了另一个过程
the reason we want to do that is because
之所以这样做是因为
procedures are going to be our ways of talking about imperative knowledge.
我们将通过程序来讨论指令性知识
And the way to make that very powerful is
这种处理方式很强大
to be able to talk about other kinds of knowledge.
我们将可以基于此来讨论其它类型的知识
So here is a procedure that, in effect, talks about another procedure,
实际上 我们讨论的是一种生成过程的过程
a general strategy that itself talks about general strategies.
一种生成通法的通法
Well, our first topic in this course--
那么 我们将主要讨论三个主题的内容
there'll be three major topics--
而首个主题则是
will be black-box abstraction.
黑盒抽象
Let's look at that in a little bit more detail.
让我们稍稍深入一点
What we're going to do is we will start out talking about
我们将讨论
how Lisp is built up out of primitive objects.
Lisp是如何通过基本对象建立起来的
What does the language supply with us?
以及Lisp的构成
And we'll see that there are primitive procedures and primitive data.
接下来 将会涉及到一些基本过程和基础数据
Then we're going to see,
然后我们将会看到
how do you take those primitives and
我们如何使用这些基本对象
combine them to make more complicated things,
并把它们组合起来构建更复杂的东西
means of combination?
及相应的组合方法
And what we'll see is that there are ways of putting things together,
后续将讨论各种进行组合的方法以及
putting primitive procedures together to make more complicated procedures.
如何用基本过程来构建更复杂的过程
And we'll see how to put primitive data together to make compound data.
同时 我们也将看到如何将基本数据组合成复合数据
Then we'll say, well, having made those compounds things,
然后我们将会介绍如何对复合数据
how do you abstract them?
如何将它们抽象出来
How do you put those black boxes around them
如何用黑盒对它们进行封装
so you can use them as components in more complex things?
使得你可以将它们作为组件用于更复杂的东西
And we'll see that's done by defining procedures and
我们会发现这些都是通过定义程序
a technique for dealing with compound data called data abstraction.
以及一种处理复合数据的数据抽象技术完成的
And then, what's maybe the most important thing,
最重要的是
is going from just the rules to how does an expert work?
我们可以从中了解到专家是如何工作的
How do you express common patterns of doing things, like saying, well,
对于找不动点的方法来讲
there's a general method of fixed point and
找平方根的方式是它的一个特例
square root is a particular case of that?
你如何表述完成工作中所存在的通用模式呢？
And we're going to use--
我们将会使用
I've already hinted at it--
之前已经提到过的
something called higher-order procedures,
某种叫做高阶过程的东西
namely procedures whose inputs and outputs are themselves procedures.
也就是说 它的输入、输出和它本身都是过程
And then we'll also see something very interesting.
我们将会看到一些有趣的东西
We'll see, as we go further and further on and become more abstract,
随着学习的深入 将会越发抽象
there'll be very--
那么将会发现
well, the line between what we consider to be data and
我们认为是数据和我们认为是过程之间的
what we consider to be procedures is going to blur at an incredible rate.
分界线将变得模糊到难以置信的程度
Well, that's our first subject, black-box abstraction.
这便是我们的第一个主题 黑盒抽象
Let's look at the second topic.
让我们来看看第二个主题
I can introduce it like this.
这样说吧
See, suppose I want to express the idea--
假设我想表达某个想法
remember, we're talking about ideas--
请注意 我们讨论的是想法
suppose I want to express the idea that
比如说
I can take something and multiply it by the sum of two other things.
我想将某个元素与另两个元素之和相乘
So for example, I might say,
举例来说
if I had 1 and 3 and multiply that by 2, I get 8.
我用1和3（之和）乘2 得8
But I'm talking about the general idea of what's called linear combination,
但我这里想讨论的是关于线性组合的基本想法
that you can add two things and multiply them by something else.
是说你可以将两个元素的和乘以另一个元素
It's very easy when I think about it for numbers,
在数集内思考这个问题是很容易的
but suppose I also want to use that same idea to think about,
但假设我想将这个想法应用于
I could add two vectors, a1 and a2,
对两向量a1和a2相加
and then scale them by some factor x and get another vector.
乘以某一因子x然后得到另一向量
Or I might say, I want to think about a1 and a2 as being polynomials,
我甚至可以说 若a1和a2皆为多项式
and I might want to add those two polynomials and
我想对这两个多项式求和
then multiply them by 2 to get a more complicated one.
然后乘以2得到一个多项式
Or a1 and a2 might be electrical signals,
同理 a1或a2也可以是电信号
and I might want to think about summing those two electrical signals and
我想将二个信号加和
then putting the whole thing through an amplifier,
并将结果放入一个放大器
multiplying it by some factor of 2 or something.
用一个类似于2的因子乘以它们
The idea is I want to think about the general notion of that.
这种想法的基本点是 我希望用一个通用记号表示它们
Now, if our language is going to be good language for expressing those kind of general ideas,
假如我们的语言可以很好的表述这类想法
if I really, really can do that,
如果真可以这样的话
I'd like to be able to say
我将会以这样的方式表述
I'm going to multiply by x the sum of a1 and a2,
用x乘以a1和a2的和
and I'd like that to express the general idea of
更进一步 我希望做更抽象更基本的表述
all different kinds of things that a1 and a2 could be.
使其可以适应各个不同类型的a1和a2
Now, if you think about that, there's a problem,
现在回过头来想想 似乎有点问题
because after all, the actual primitive operations
毕竟 对两个数字和两个多项式进行加和运算
that go on in the machine are obviously going to be different
所用的基本操作
if I'm adding two numbers than if I'm adding two polynomials,
在机器内部显然是不同的
or if I'm adding the representation of two electrical signals or wave forms.
对两个电信号或声波加和也有同样的问题
Somewhere, there has to be the knowledge of the kinds of various things
无论怎样 对不同类型的元素进行求和运算
that you can add and the ways of adding them.
总是需要使用不同的方法
Now, to construct such a system,
现在 为了构建这样一个系统
the question is, where do I put that knowledge?
我们将如何使用这些知识呢？
How do I think about the different kinds of choices I have?
如何在各种方法中进行选择？
And if tomorrow George comes up with a new kind of object
而如果明天George又想出了一种新类型的对象
that might be added and multiplied,
并将它用于加和以及乘积
how do I add George's new object to the system
我又该如何把这个新类型引入到系统中
without screwing up everything that was already there?
而且能够做到不把已有的系统弄得一团糟？
Well, that's going to be the second big topic,
这便是我们的第二大主题
the way of controlling that kind of complexity.
控制复杂度的方法
And the way you do that is by establishing conventional interfaces,
我们实现的方法是按照约定来实现相应的接口
agreed upon ways of plugging things together.
并以此将各部分组合起来
Just like in electrical engineering,
就如同电气工程中
people have standard impedances for connectors,
人们为连接器规定标准阻抗
and then you know if you build something with one of those standard impedances,
如果用符合这个标准的东西来构建系统
you can plug it together with something else.
你就知道你可以把各个部件组合在一起
So that's going to be our second large topic, conventional interfaces.
这就是我们将要讨论的第二个主题：约定接口
What we're going to see is, first, we're going to talk about the problem of generic operations,
如我之前提到的
which is the one I alluded to,
接下来我们将讨论通用操作中的问题
things like "plus" that have to work with all different kinds of data.
例如对各种不同类型数据进行均适用的加法操作
So we talk about generic operations.
随后则会讨论通用操作
Then we're going to talk about really large-scale structures.
然后我们将讨论大型架构问题
How do you put together very large programs
如果通过对现实世界的复杂系统建模
that model the kinds of complex systems in the real world that you'd like to model?
来构建大型程序
And what we're going to see is that
我们将看到 在构建这样的系统时
there are two very important metaphors for putting together such systems.
有两种非常重要的方法
One is called object-oriented programming,
其一是面向对象编程
where you sort of think of your system as a kind of society
在这种模式中 你把你的系统想象成一个社区
full of little things that interact by sending information between them.
社区中的各个部分都是通过相互间传递消息联系起来的
And then the second one is operations on aggregates, called streams,
其二是关于聚集的操作 称作“流”
where you think of a large system put together kind of
使用这种方式构建大型系统
like a signal processing engineer puts together a large electrical system.
类似于电气工程师构造大型电气系统
That's going to be our second topic.
这就是我们的第二个话题
Now, the third thing we're going to come to,
现在 我们将要讨论第三个话题
the third basic technique for controlling complexity,
控制复杂度的第三个技术
is making new languages.
便是定义新的语言
Because sometimes, when you're sort of overwhelmed by the complexity of a design,
因为有时 当你有点受不了设计的复杂度时
the way that you control that complexity is to pick a new design language.
你可以通过定义一门新的语言来控制系统复杂度
And the purpose of the new design language will be to highlight different aspects of the system.
新语言的设计意图是为了强调系统的某个方面
It will suppress some kinds of details and emphasize other kinds of details.
它一方面隐藏了部分细节 另一方面则但强调一些其他的细节
This is going to be the most magical part of the course.
这部分将是课程中最神奇的部分
We're going to start out by actually looking at the technology for building new computer languages.
我们将开始于构建新的计算机语言
The first thing we're going to do is actually build in Lisp.
实际上我们首先要完成的工作已经内建于Lisp之中了
We're going to express in Lisp the process of interpreting Lisp itself.
我们将展现如何用Lisp来解释Lisp
And that's going to be a very sort of self-circular thing.
这是一个非常类似于自循环的过程
There's a little mystical symbol that has to do with that.
这与（Lisp中）一个神奇的符号有关
The process of interpreting Lisp is sort of a giant wheel of two processes,
解释Lisp的步骤是
apply and eval,
应用和求值——这两大步骤的轮转
which sort of constantly reduce expressions to each other.
这两者不断地互相交替进行
Then we're going to see all sorts of other magical things.
接下来 我们将看到其余神奇的东西
Here's another magical symbol.
譬如另一种魔法符号
This is sort of the Y operator,
一种叫做Y运算符的东西
which is, in some sense, the expression of infinity inside our procedural language.
某种意义上 它在过程式语言中用于 表达无限
We'll take a look at that.
我们也会谈论到它
In any case, this section of the course is called Metalinguistic Abstraction,
总之 这部分课程被称作“元语言抽象”
abstracting by talking about how you construct new languages.
主要讨论如何构建一门新语言
As I said, we're going to start out by looking at the process of interpretation.
如我所言 我们将从了解解释的过程开始
We're going to look at this apply-eval loop, and build Lisp.
随后则一起讨论应用-求值循环和构建Lisp
Then, just to show you that this is very general,
你将发现这种方法具有相当的普遍性
we're going to use exactly the same technology to build a very different kind of language,
我们将用同样的技术去构建一门全完不同的语言
a so-called logic programming language,
一种所谓的逻辑编程语言
where you don't really talk about procedures at all that have inputs and outputs.
一种无关具有输入和输出的过程
What you do is talk about relations between things.
而仅关注元素之间关系的语言
And then finally, we're going to talk about how you implement these things very concretely
最终 我们将讨论如何将这些东西
on the very simplest kind of machines.
实实在在的实现在简单的机器上
We'll see something like this.
比如说这个
This is a picture of a chip,
如图所示的芯片
which is the Lisp interpreter that we will be talking about then in hardware.
就是我们在硬件部分谈及的Lisp解释器
Well, there's an outline of the course, three big topics.
这三大主题就是本课的提纲
Black-box abstraction, conventional interfaces, metalinguistic abstraction.
黑盒抽象 约定接口 元语言抽象
Now, let's take a break now and then we'll get started.
好 先休息一会儿 然后正式开始
[JESU, JOY OF MAN'S DESIRING]
[音乐]
Let's actually start in learning Lisp now.
现在让我们正式开始学习Lisp
Actually, we'll start out by learning something much more important,
事实上 我们将开始学习一些非常重要的内容
maybe the very most important thing in this course, which is not Lisp,
在这门课程中最重要的 不是Lisp本身
in particular, of course, but rather a general framework
而是一种的通用框架体系
for thinking about languages that I already alluded to.
我们用它来组织我之前提到的语言
When somebody tells you they're going to show you a language,
当有人要向你展示一门新语言
what you should say is,
你应该问他
what I'd like you to tell me is what are the primitive elements?
（构成语言的）基本元素有哪些？
What does the language come with?
这门语言使用哪些基本元素？
Then, what are the ways you put those together?
你是如何将这些元素组合在一起的？
What are the means of combination?
组合的方法是什么？
What are the things that allow you to take these primitive elements
允许你将这些基本元素整合在一起
and build bigger things out of them?
以构建更大的对象的又是什么？
What are the ways of putting things together?
把东西构建在一起的方法是什么？
And then, what are the means of abstraction?
以及 抽象的方法是什么？
How do we take those complicated things and draw those boxes around them?
我们如何利用这些元素并把它们封装成盒子？
How do we name them so that we can now use them
我们如何为它们命名使得我们可以
as if they were primitive elements in making still more complex things?
把它们当作基本元素来用于构建更复杂的东西？
And so on, and so on, and so on.
等等 等等 等等
So when someone says to you, gee,
因此 当有人告诉你
I have a great new computer language,
嘿 我发明了一种新的计算机语言
you don't say, how many characters does it take to invert a matrix?
你不应该问 用你的语言编写求逆矩阵需要多少代码
It's irrelevant.
这是风马牛不相及的
What you say is, if the language did not come with matrices built in
如果该语言没有内建了矩阵或者类似的东西
or with something else built in,
那你就应该问他
how could I then build that thing?
应该如何构建矩阵？
What are the means of combination which would allow me to do that?
如何通过组合来构建？
And then, what are the means of abstraction
如何对其进行抽象
which allow me then to use those as elements
把它作为基本元素
in making more complicated things yet?
来构建更复杂的东西？
Well, we're going to see that Lisp has some primitive data and some primitive procedures.
我们将了解到Lisp的一些基本数据和基本过程
In fact, let's really start.
好吧 这次是真的开始了
And here's a piece of primitive data in Lisp, number 3.
这里有一个Lisp的基本数据 数字3
Actually, if I'm being very pedantic, that's not the number 3.
事实上 如果打破沙锅问到底的话 这不是数字3
That's some symbol that represents Plato's concept of the number 3.
这只是一个符号 用以代表柏拉图观念下的数字3的
And here's another.
这又是另一个
Here's some more primitive data in Lisp, 17.4.
这个是Lisp中又一个基本数据 17.4
Or actually, some representation of 17.4.
又或者说 代表17.4
And here's another one, 5.
这儿还有一个5
Here's another primitive object that's built in Lisp, addition.
然后这儿又有一个内建于Lisp的基本对象“+”
Actually, to use the same kind of pedantic--
如果又要继续深究的话
this is a name for the primitive method of adding things.
这只是一个名字 代表对元素进行加和的基本方法而已
Just like this is a name for Plato's number 3,
就像这个是柏拉图式的3
this is a name for Plato's concept of how you add things.
这也只是一个代表柏拉图观念下的将某些元素加和起来
So those are some primitive elements.
这些都是基本元素
I can put them together.
我可以将它们放在一起
I can say, gee, what's the sum of 3 and 17.4 and 5?
我可以说 3加17.4加5的和是多少
And the way I do that is to say,
这等同于说
let's apply the sum operator to these three numbers.
让我们把求和运算符应用于这三个数
And I should get, what? 8, 17. 25.4.
我可以得到什么呢 是8 是17 还是25.4
So I should be able to ask Lisp what the value of this is,
因此 我可以问Lisp这个的值是多少
and it will return 25.4.
（表达式）返回25.4
Let's introduce some names.
介绍一些术语吧
This thing that I typed is called a combination.
我所写的这些东西就叫做组合式
And a combination consists, in general, of applying an operator--
通常 一个组合式是由运算符
so this is an operator--
这些就是运算符
to some operands.
和应用该运算符的运算对象组成
These are the operands.
这些是运算对象
And of course, I can make more complex things.
当然 我可以完成更复杂的事
The reason I can get complexity out of this is because the operands themselves,
我可以使之更复杂是因为 这些运算对象
in general, can be combinations.
通常来说 也可以是组合式
So for instance, I could say, what is the sum of 3 and the product of 5 and 6 and 8 and 2?
比如 3加上5乘以6乘以8乘以2的积的和是多少
And I should get-- let's see-- 30, 40, 43.
而我应该得到 我算一下 30 40 43
So Lisp should tell me that that's 43.
因此Lisp会返回这个表达式的值是43
Forming combinations is the basic needs of combination that we'll be looking at.
后续我们将看到构造组合式是组合的基本需求
And then, well, you see some syntax here.
你所看到的这些语法
Lisp uses what's called prefix notation,
就是Lisp用的所谓的前缀表示法
which means that the operator is written to the left of the operands.
意即操作符在操作数的左端
It's just a convention.
这只是个约定
And notice, it's fully parenthesized.
注意 这些都被括起来了
And the parentheses make it completely unambiguous.
这些括号使得它们区别开来
So by looking at this, I can see that there's the operator,
因此只要看看这个 我就可以知道这个是运算符
and there are 1, 2, 3, 4 operands.
以及这有1个 2个 3个 4个运算对象
And I can see that the second operand here is itself some combination
而且我也可以发现第二个运算对象是个组合式
that has one operator and two operands.
该组合式有一个运算符和两个运算对象
Parentheses in Lisp are a little bit,
Lisp中的括号 有点或者非常不同于
or are very unlike parentheses in conventional mathematics.
通常数学中的括号
In mathematics, we sort of use them to mean grouping,
数学中 我们常将其用于分组
and it sort of doesn't hurt if sometimes you leave out parentheses
如果有时你忘了闭合括号 但其他人能理解你的意图
if people understand that that's a group.
这也无关紧要
And in general, it doesn't hurt if you put in extra parentheses,
通常的 你多加了括号也无所谓
because that maybe makes the grouping more distinct.
因为这样只会使得分组更加明确
Lisp is not like that.
Lisp可不像这样
In Lisp, you cannot leave out parentheses,
Lisp中你既不能不闭合括号
and you cannot put in extra parentheses,
亦不能添加多余的括号
because putting in parentheses always means,
因为加括号总是意味着
exactly and precisely, this is a combination which has meaning,
确切的来说 所括之物是一个组合式
applying operators to operands.
表示将运算符应用于运算对象
And if I left this out, if I left those parentheses out,
如果我不闭合这个括号
it would mean something else.
这个就变成其它的意思了
In fact, the way to think about this,
事实上 我们可以这么来理解这个问题
is really what I'm doing when I write something like this is writing a tree.
把我写的这些东西想作一个树
So this combination is a tree that has a plus and
这个组合式实际上是一个树 树具有一个“+”
then a 3 and then a something else and an 8 and a 2.
以及 一个3和一些其它的东西和一个8 还有一个2
And then this something else here is
而这里的其它的东西
itself a little subtree that has a star and a 5 and a 6.
它本身是一个有一个“*”一个5和一个6的子树
And the way to think of that is, really,
我们可以这样认为
what's going on are we're writing these trees,
我们只是在构建这些树而已
and parentheses are just a way to write this two-dimensional structure
括号只是将这种二维结构写作线性字符串
as a linear character string.
的一种方法罢了
Because at least when Lisp first started and people had teletypes or punch cards or whatever,
因为至少在Lisp发明时 人们还在用电传打字机或者打孔卡
this was more convenient.
这种记法方便多了
Maybe if Lisp started today, the syntax of Lisp would look like that.
如果Lisp是在当下被发明的 语法可能会像树那样
Well, let's look at what that actually looks like on the computer.
那么 让我们看看在计算机里面它究竟是什么样
Here I have a Lisp interaction set up.
这里有个Lisp解释套件
There's a editor.
这是个编辑器
And on the top, I'm going to type some values and ask Lisp what they are.
我将要在上方写一些表达式并让Lisp对其求值
So for instance, I can say to Lisp,
比如 我可以问Lisp
what's the value of that symbol?
这个符号的值是多少
That's 3.
我键入3
And I ask Lisp to evaluate it.
然后叫Lisp对其求值
And there you see Lisp has returned on the bottom,
然后你就会看到Lisp在下面返回了一些信息
and said, oh yeah, that's 3.
这个值就是3
Or I can say, what's the sum of 3 and 4 and 8?
我也可以问 3加上4加上8的和是多少
What's that combination?
键入这个组合式
And ask Lisp to evaluate it.
让Lisp对其求值
That's 15.
返回15
Or I can type in something more complicated.
我可以键入一些更复杂的东西
I can say, what's the sum of the product of 3 and the sum of 7 and 19.5?
将3乘以7加19.5的和的乘积求和得多少
And you'll notice here that Lisp has something built in
你会发现Lisp内建了一些功能
that helps me keep track of all these parentheses.
帮你跟踪这些括号
Watch as I type the next closed parentheses,
看我键入下一个右圆括号
which is going to close the combination starting with the star.
用于闭合以“*”开头的那个组合式
The opening one will flash.
开头的那个左括号会闪一下
Here, I'll rub those out and do it again.
我把这些括号擦去 再示范一次
Type close, and you see that closes the plus.
键入右括号 闭合了“+”组合式
Close again, that closes the star.
再键入右括号 闭合了“*”组合式
Now I'm back to the sum, and maybe I'm going to add that all to 4.
现在我又回到了加 我将它们与4相加
That closes the plus.
闭合了“+”组合式
Now I have a complete combination, and I can ask Lisp for the value of that.
现在我补全了组合式 然后我问Lisp它们的值是多少
That kind of paren balancing is something that's built into
这种内建于各种Lisp系统的
a lot of Lisp systems to help you keep track,
括号匹配工具帮你跟进（括号匹配）
because it is kind of hard just by hand doing all these parentheses.
因为手工闭合这些括号太辛苦了
There's another kind of convention for keeping track of parentheses.
这又是另外一种保持括号跟进的约定
Let me write another complicated combination.
我另外写一个复杂的组合式
Let's take the sum of the product of 3 and 5 and add that to something.
将3和5的积与某个元素求和
And now what I'm going to do is
现在我将要缩进
I'm going to indent so that the operands are written vertically.
使得这些运算对象都是垂直书写的
Which the sum of that and the product of 47 and--
将这些加上47乘以
let's say the product of 47 with a difference of 20 and 6.8.
恩…… 47乘以20和6.8的差
That means subtract 6.8 from 20.
意即从20中减去6.8
And then you see the parentheses close.
然后 这个括号闭合了
Close the minus. Close the star.
闭合“-” 闭合“*”
And now let's get another operator.
现在 我们再写一个运算符
You see the Lisp editor here is indenting to the right position automatically
Lisp编辑器自动缩进到正确的位置
to help me keep track.
来帮助我保持跟进
I'll do that again.
我再示范一次
I'll close that last parentheses again.
这样就又闭合了最后一个括号
You see it balances the plus.
它匹配了这个“+”（的括号）
Now I can say, what's the value of that?
现在我想问 这个的值是多少
So those two things, indenting to the right level,
因此 这两件事 缩进到正确的位置
which is called pretty printing,
也就是所谓的美观的输出
and flashing parentheses,
以及闭合提示
are two things that a lot of Lisp systems have built in to help you keep track.
是许多Lisp系统所内建用于帮你保持跟进的工具
And you should learn how to use them.
你应该学习如何使用它们
Ok, those are the primitives.
好 这些都是基本的内容
There's a means of combination.
这就是一种组合的方法
Now let's go up to the means of abstraction.
现在让我们来看看抽象的方法
I'd like to be able to take the idea that I do some combination like this,
我希望我能够写一些像这样的组合式
and abstract it and give it a simple name,
将它抽象化并给它命名
so I can use that as an element.
使得我可以将其作为一个（我们语言的）元素
And I do that in Lisp with "define."
在Lisp中 我可以用“define”来实现
So I can say, for example,
比如说
define A to be the product of 5 and 5.
定义A为5乘以5
And now I could say, for example, to Lisp,
现在我可以问Lisp
what is the product of A and A?
A和A的乘积是多少
And this should be 25, and this should be 625.
这个是25所以这个就是625
And then, crucial thing, I can now use A--
但更重要的则是 我现在可以使用A
here I've used it in a combination--
我已经在这个组合式里面用过了
but I could use that in other more complicated things that I name in turn.
但我也可以在更复杂的组合式里面使用它
So I could say, define B to be the sum of,
我也可以说 定义B为
we'll say, A and the product of 5 and A.
A与5乘以A的积的和
And then close the plus.
闭合“+”
Let's take a look at that on the computer and see how that looks.
让我们来看看它在计算机中是怎样的吧
So I'll just type what I wrote on the board.
我就像黑板上写的那样键入就可以了
I could say, define A to be the product of 5 and 5.
我告诉Lisp
And I'll tell that to Lisp.
定义A为5乘以5的积
And notice what Lisp responded there with was an A in the bottom.
注意Lisp在下方回应了一个A
In general, when you type in a definition in Lisp,
通常来说 你如果在Lisp中键入了一个定义
it responds with the symbol being defined.
它返回被定义的符号
Now I could say to Lisp, what is the product of A and A?
现在我问Lisp A乘以A的积是多少
And it says that's 625.
Lisp返回625
I can define B to be the sum of A and the product of 5 and A.
我也可以定义B为A加上5乘以A的积的和
Close a paren closes the star.  Close the plus. Close the "define."
闭合“*” 闭合“+” 闭合“define”
Lisp says, OK, B, there on the bottom.
Lisp在下方正常返回B
And now I can say to Lisp, what's the value of B?
现在我可以问Lisp B的值是多少
And I can say something more complicated,
我也可以问一些更复杂的事
like what's the sum of A and the quotient of B and 5?
比如A加上B除以5的商的和是多少
That slash is divide, another primitive operator.
这个“/”是另一个基本运算符 代表除
I've divided B by 5, added it to A.
我让B除以5 并加在A上
Lisp says, OK, that's 55.
Lisp正常返回55
So there's what it looks like.
就像这样
There's the basic means of defining something.
这是定义东西的基本方法
It's the simplest kind of naming, but it's not really very powerful.
这是最简单的命名方法 但并不是很强大
See, what I'd really like to name--
注意我们讨论的是通用方法
remember, we're talking about general methods--
因此我真正想定义的是
I'd like to name, oh, the general idea that, for example,
一种通用方法 可以
I could multiply 5 by 5, or 6 by 6, or 1,001 by 1,001, 1,001.7 by 1,001.7.
得到 5乘5 6乘6 1001乘1001 1001.7乘1001.7
I'd like to be able to name the general idea of multiplying something by itself.
我想给一个数与其自身相乘这种想法一个名字
Well, you know what that is. That's called squaring.
你应该知道 这叫做平方
And the way I can do that in Lisp is I can say,
而在Lisp中我应该这样实现
define to square something x, multiply x by itself.
定义 square某个叫x的东西 为 将x乘以x自己
And then having done that, I could say to Lisp,
定义完毕后 我可以问Lisp
for example, what's the square of 10?
比如 10的平方是多少
And Lisp will say 100.
Lisp返回100
So now let's actually look at that a little more closely.
让我们深入讨论一下
Right, there's the definition of square.
这儿是square的定义
To square something, multiply it by itself.
square某个元素 即是将该元素进行自乘
You see this x here.
这里的x
That x is kind of a pronoun,
应该算是一种代词
which is the something that I'm going to square.
指代了我要做平方的元素
And what I do with it is I multiply x, I multiply it by itself.
实际上我将其乘以x 即是乘以它自己
OK. So there's the notation for defining a procedure.
这些就是定义一个过程的记法
Actually, this is a little bit confusing,
这样说可能把你搞糊涂了
because this is sort of how I might use square.
因为这就像我在用square一样
And I say square root of x or square root of 10,
但如果我说x的平方根或者10的平方根
but it's not making it very clear that I'm actually naming something.
并没有说清楚我对什么做了定义
So let me write this definition in another way
所以让我换个方式来进行定义
that makes it a little bit more clear that I'm naming something.
这样可以清楚的看到定义的具体内容
I'll say, "define" square to be lambda of x times xx.
我定义“square”为“(lambda (x) (* x x))”
Here, I'm naming something square, just like over here, I'm naming something A.
这里 我定义square就像我某命名为A一样
The thing that I'm naming square--
我定义square
here, the thing I named A was the value of this combination.
这里 我把这个组合式的值命名为A
Here, the thing that I'm naming square is this thing
在这里 我把这个东西命名为square
that begins with lambda,
以lambda开头
and lambda is Lisp's way of saying make a procedure.
lambda在Lisp中用以构建一个过程
Let's look at that more closely on the slide.
请仔细看一下幻灯片上的内容
The way I read that definition is to say,
这个定义读作
I define square to be make a procedure--
将square定义为
that's what the lambda is--
一个由lambda构造的
make a procedure with an argument named x.
一个有带有参数x的过程
And what it does is return the results of multiplying x by itself.
而该过程返回将x自乘的结果
Now, in general, we're going to be using this top form of defining,
一般来讲 这是最佳的定义方式
just because it's a little bit more convenient.
因为这个更加方便一点
But don't lose sight of the fact that it's really this.
但是也别忘了它实质上也是这个
In fact, as far as the Lisp interpreter's concerned,
事实上 就Lisp解释器而言
there's no difference between typing this to it and typing this to it.
这两种方法没有区别
And there's a word for that, sort of syntactic sugar.
换句话说 这只是一种语法糖
What syntactic sugar means,
语法糖的意思就是
it's having somewhat more convenient surface forms for typing something.
这种形式输入更方便一些
So this is just really syntactic sugar for this underlying Greek thing with the lambda.
这只是这下面的有lambda的表达式的语法糖而已
And the reason you should remember that is don't forget that,
你应该记住
when I write something like this, I'm really naming something.
当我这样写的时候 其实是在对某个东西进行命名
I'm naming something square,
我将其命名为square
and the something that I'm naming square is a procedure that's getting constructed.
square代表一个构建好的过程
Well, let's look at that on the computer, too.
让我们看看在计算机里面又是 怎样的吧
So I'll come and I'll say, define square of x to be times xx.
定义“(square x)”为x乘以x的积
Now I'll tell Lisp that.
将它送入Lisp
It says "square."
返回square
See, I've named something "square."
现在 我已经将某个东西命名为square了
Now, having done that, I can ask Lisp for, what's the square of 1,001?
完毕后 我就可以问Lisp 1001的平方是多少
Or in general, I could say, what's the square of the sum of 5 and 7?
或者更通常的来说 我可以问 5加上7的和的平方是多少
The square of 12's 144.
12的平方是144
Or I can use square itself as an element in some combination.
在某些组合式中我亦可把square当作一个元素
I can say, what's the sum of the square of 3 and the square of 4?
3的平方加上4的平方的和是多少
9 and 16 is 25.
9加上16得25
Or I can use square as an element in some much more complicated thing.
我可以将square作为元素用于更复杂的式子
I can say, what's the square of, the sqare of, the square of 1,001?
比如 1001的平方点的平方的平方是多少
And there's the square of the square of the square of 1,001.
这就是1001点的平方的平方的平方
Or I can say to Lisp, what is square itself?
我也可以问Lisp square本身是什么
What's the value of that?
它的值是是什么
And Lisp returns some conventional way of telling me that that's a procedure.
Lisp用一种约定的方法告诉我这是一个过程
It says, "compound procedure square."
它返回 复合过程square
Remember, the value of square is this procedure,
记住 square的值是一个过程
and the thing with the stars and the brackets
而那些用星号和括号的记法
are just Lisp's conventional way of describing that.
只是Lisp用来描述这个过程的约定
Let's look at two more examples of defining.
让我们再看两个关于define的例子
Here are two more procedures.
这有两个过程
I can define the average of x and y to be the sum of x and y divided by 2.
定义x和y的平均值为x加上y的和除以2的商
Or having had average and mean square, having had average and square,
以及定义好平方和平均值后 我可以定义均方
I can use that to talk about the mean square of something,
我可以用它们来讨论某元素的均方
which is the average of the square of x and the square of y.
即x的平方与y的平方的平均值
So for example, having done that, I could say,
当定义好它们后 我可以问
what's the mean square of 2 and 3?
2和3的均方是多少
And I should get the average of 4 and 9, which is 6.5.
我将会得到 4和9的平均值 即6.5
The key thing here is that, having defined square,
关键点在于 定义了square后
I can use it as if it were primitive.
我可以把它当作一个基本元素来使用
So if we look here on the slide,
因此在这里
if I look at mean square,
我在讨论均方的时候
the person defining mean square doesn't have to know, at this point,
从这点来说 定义均方的人没有必要知道
whether square was something built into the language
究竟square是由语言内建支持
or whether it was a procedure that was defined.
还是自定义的过程
And that's a key thing in Lisp,
这是Lisp的关键之一
that you do not make arbitrary distinctions between things
你无法准确区别
that happen to be primitive in the language and things that happen to be built in.
哪些是语言的基本对象 哪些是语言的内建支持
A person using that shouldn't even have to know.
用户使用时则无需关心这些
So the things you construct get used with all the power and flexibility
你自己构建的东西看起来就像是语言自带的基本对象
as if they were primitives.
具有同样的能力和灵活性
In fact, you can drive that home by looking on the computer one more time.
大家可以在课后上机做做测试
We talked about plus.
我们接下来讨论一下“+”吧
And in fact, if I come here on the computer screen and say,
好的 让我们在计算机中看看
what is the value of plus?
“+”的值是什么
Notice what Lisp types out. On the bottom there, it typed out,
注意Lisp在下面的输出
"compound procedure plus."
复合过程“+”
Because, in this system,
因为在此系统中
it turns out that the addition operator is itself a compound procedure.
“+”运算符是一个复合过程
And if I didn't just type that in, you'd never know that,
但如果我不输入进去做下测试 你永远不会知道
and it wouldn't make any difference anyway.
所以这没什么不同
We don't care.
我们并不关心这些
It's below the level of the abstraction that we're dealing with.
它比我们日常处理的问题更加抽象一些
So the key thing is you cannot tell, should not be able to tell, in general,
其关键点在于你无法分辨出
the difference between things that are built in and things that are compound.
内建元素与复合元素之间的不同
Why is that?
为什么会这样呢？
Because the things that are compound have an abstraction wrapper wrapped around them.
因为复合元素经过了一次抽象封装 (以致于无法分辨)
We've seen almost all the elements of Lisp now.
我们已经介绍了Lisp的大多数元素了
There's only one more we have to look at,
还有一个需要进行讨论的
and that is how to make a case analysis.
就是如何进行分情况分析
Let me show you what I mean.
举个例子
We might want to think about the mathematical definition of the absolute value functions.
让我们考虑绝对值函数的数学定义
I might say the absolute value of x is the function
我或许会说x的绝对值这样是一个函数
which has the property that it's negative of x. For x less than 0,
若x小于0 则为-x
it's 0 for x equal to 0.
若x等于0 则为0
And it's x for x greater than 0.
若x大于0 则就是x
And Lisp has a way of making case analyses.
而Lisp则有一套分情况分析方法
Let me define for you absolute value.
以绝对值定义为例 我给大家说明一下
Say define the absolute value of x is conditional.
定义绝对值为 x是有多种情况的
This means case analysis, COND.
这就是分情况分析
If x is less than 0, the answer is negate x.
如果x小于0 则结果为-x
What I've written here is a clause.
我这里写的是一个子句
This whole thing is a conditional clause, and it has two parts.
这整个是一个由两部分组成的条件表达式
This part here is a predicate or a condition.
这个部分叫做谓词或者条件
That's a condition.
这就是一种情况（条件）
And the condition is expressed by something called a predicate,
用以表达条件的东西叫做谓词
and a predicate in Lisp is some sort of thing
Lisp中的谓词是一种
that returns either true or false.
可以返回true或者false的东西
And you see Lisp has a primitive procedure, less-than,
比如说“小于”是Lisp中的一个基本过程
that tests whether something is true or false.
它返回true或者false
And the other part of a clause is an action or a thing to do,
子句其余部分为一个动作或者需要做的事
in the case where that's true.
本例中为true
And here, what I'm doing is negating x.
在这里 我则是取x的相反数
The negation operator, the minus sign in Lisp is a little bit funny.
有趣的是 Lisp中减运算符符与相反数运算符相同
If there's two or more arguments,
如果有两个及两个以上的参数
if there's two arguments it subtracts the second one from the first, and we saw that.
正如我们看到的 假设刚好有两个参数 就从第一个中减去第二个
And if there's one argument, it negates it.
如果只有一个参数 则取其相反数
So this corresponds to that.
这与前面相符合
And then there's another COND clause.
这又是一个COND子句
It says, in the case where x is equal to 0, the answer is 0.
这是说 在x等于0的时候 结果为0
And in the case where x is greater than 0, the answer is x.
在x大于0的时候 结果为x
Close that clause. Close the COND. Close the definition.
闭合子句 闭合COND 闭合define
And there's the definition of absolute value.
这就是绝对值的定义
And you see it's the case analysis that looks very much
你会发现分情况分析
like the case analysis you use in mathematics.
与数学中所用的非常相似
There's a somewhat different way of writing a restricted case analysis.
当然还有一些不常用的受限的分情况分析方法
Often, you have a case analysis where you only have one case,
很多时候 你在进行分情况分析时只有一种情况
where you test something,
你首先进行测试
and then depending on whether it's true or false, you do something.
然后根据返回的为true或false来决定如何处理
And here's another definition of absolute value
这是另外一种定义绝对值的方法
which looks almost the same,
但看起来是几乎一样的
which says, if x is less than 0, the result is negate x.
像这样 如果x小于0 结果则为x的相反数
Otherwise, the answer is x.
否则 结果即为x
And we'll be using "if" a lot.
我们将会大量的使用“if”
But again, the thing to remember is that
再次声明
this form of absolute value that you're looking at here,
你们在这里看到的绝对值形式
and then this one over here that I wrote on the board,
和我在黑板上写的那种
are essentially the same.
本质上是一样的
And "if" and COND are-- well, whichever way you like it.
而“if”和“COND”则是——
You can think of COND as syntactic sugar for "if",
你可以把“COND”当做“if”的语法糖
or you can think of "if" as syntactic sugar for COND,
或者“if”是“COND”的语法糖
and it doesn't make any difference.
这没什么区别
The person implementing a Lisp system will pick one
Lisp系统的设计者会从中会选择一个
and implement the other in terms of that.
然后依照这个来实现另外一个
And it doesn't matter which one you pick.
你首先实现哪一个都无所谓
Why don't we break now, and then take some questions.
让我们停下来 解决几点疑问
How come sometimes when I write define,
为什么我有时用define时
I put an open paren here and say,
我在这里使用了一个左括号
define open paren something or other,
输入 define (XXX
and sometimes when I write this, I don't put an open paren?
而有时我这样写时却没加左括号
The answer is, this particular form of "define",
是因为你所见的
where you say define some expression,
这种“define”表达式
is this very special thing for defining procedures.
对于定义过程来讲是非常特殊
But again, what it really means is I'm defining this symbol, square, to be that.
再次强调 这实际上是说我定义这个叫square的符号为这个
So the way you should think about it is what "define" does is you write "define",
你所知道的则是 你先写一个“define”
and the second thing you write is the symbol here-- no open paren--
然后你再写一个符号 没有左括号
the symbol you're defining
这是你将要定义的符号
and what you're defining it to be.
这又是你要将其定义为什么
That's like here and like here.
就像这儿和这儿
That's sort of the basic way you use "define."
这是“define”的基本使用方法
And then, there's this special syntactic trick
然而 这种特殊的语法技巧
which allows you to define procedures that look like this.
使得你可以定义像这样的过程
So the difference is, it's whether or not you're defining a procedure.
因此区别就在于你是否定义了一个过程
[JESU, JOY OF MAN'S DESIRING]
[音乐]
Well, believe it or not, you actually now know enough Lisp
信不信由你 你们已经学了足够多的Lisp的知识了
to write essentially any numerical procedure
现在你基本上可以编写
that you'd write in a language like FORTRAN or Basic or whatever,
FORTRAN、Basic或者其它语言中一样的
or, essentially, any other language.
数值计算过程了
And you're probably saying, that's not believable,
或许你会说 这不可能
because you know that these languages have things
因为你知道这些语言有
like "for statements", and "do until while" or something.
像“for”语句和“do-until-whil”语句的东西
But we don't really need any of that.
实际上这些我们一点也用不着
In fact, we're not going to use any of that in this course.
本课中我们一点也不会使用这些东西
Let me show you.
我给你们来个下马威
Again, looking back at square root,
回过头来看看平方根
let's go back to this square root algorithm of Heron of Alexandria.
让我们看看亚历山大的Heron提出的平方根算法
Remember what that said.
想想它是怎么说的
It said, to find an approximation to the square root of X,
算法说 为了找到X的平方根的近似值
you make a guess,
你做出猜测
you improve that guess by averaging the guess and X over the guess.
然后通过取guess和X/guess的平均数来改进猜测
You keep improving that until the guess is good enough.
你不断改进猜测 直到这个猜测足够好
I already alluded to the idea.
我已经提到过这种想法
The idea is that, if the initial guess that you took
这种想法是说 如果你最初采用的猜测
was actually equal to the square root of X,
真真切切的等于X的平方根
then G here would be equal to X/G.
那么G就会等于X/G
So if you hit the square root, averaging them wouldn't change it.
如果你算出平方根 对其取平均数并不会改变它
If the G that you picked was larger than the square root of X,
如果你所采用的G比X的平方根大
then X/G will be smaller than the square root of X,
那么X/G就会比X的平方根小
so that when you average G and X/G,
因此当你取G与X/G的平均值时
you get something in between.
就得到了两者之间的某数
So if you pick a G that's too small, your answer will be too large.
同理 若你采用的G过小 答案则会过大
If you pick a G that's too large,
如果你采用了一个太大的G
if your G is larger than the square root of X
如果你的G比X的平方根还要大的话
and X/G will be smaller than the square root of X.
X/G就会比X的平方根还要小
So averaging always gives you something in between.
因此取平均值使得你总可以得到两者间的某数
And then, it's not quite trivial, but it's possible to show that,
这不是毫无意义的 它表明
in fact, if G misses the square root of X by a little bit,
事实上 如果G只差X的平方根一点的话
the average of G and X/G will actually keep getting closer to the square root of X.
G和X/G的平均值就会慢慢的向X的平方根靠近
So if you keep doing this enough,
只要你不断的这样做
you'll eventually get as close as you want.
最终就可以不断地靠近
And then there's another fact,
另外一个事实则是
that you can always start out this process by using 1 as an initial guess.
你总可以使用1作为一个初始猜测值来开始计算
And it'll always converge to the square root of X.
它总是朝X的平方根聚拢
So that's this method of successive averaging due to Heron of Alexandria.
这就是亚历山大的Heron的连续求平均值法
Let's write it in Lisp.
让我们在Lisp中实现
Well, the central idea is,
中心思想是
what does it mean to try a guess for the square root of X?
尝试将guess作为X的平方根的一个猜想意味着什么
Let's write that.
我来编码
So we'll say, define to try a guess for the square root of X,
定义（try guess x）
what do we do? We'll say,
我们该如何做 我们会说
if the guess is good enough to be a guess for the square root of X,
如果猜测精确到可以作为X的平方根
then, as an answer, we'll take the guess.
那么我们就可以将这个猜测作为答案
Otherwise, we will try the improved guess.
否则 我们就会尝试改进猜测
We'll improve that guess for the square root of X,
我们将通过改进这个猜测来作为X的平方根
and we'll try that as a guess for the square root of X.
并尝试是否为X平方根
Close the "try." Close the "if." Close the "define."
闭合try 闭合if 闭合define
So that's how we try a guess.
这就是我们如何尝试一个猜测
And then, the next part of the process said,
然后 这个过程的下一步是说
in order to compute square roots, we'll say,
为了计算平方根
define to compute the square root of X,
定义计算X的平方根为
we will try 1 as a guess for the square root of X.
从1作为X的平方根的一个猜测开始尝试
Well, we have to define a couple more things.
我们必须定义一些其它的东西
We have to say, how is a guess good enough?
我们必须说明 一个猜测如何才叫“足够好”
And how do we improve a guess?
我们又该如何改进这个猜测
So let's look at that.
那么让我们来看看
The algorithm to improve a guess for the square root of X,
而改进一个X的平方根的一个猜测的算法则是
we average-- that was the algorithm--
取平均数
we average the guess with the quotient of dividing X by the guess.
我们取guess和X/guess的平均数
That's how we improve a guess.
这就是我们如何改进一个猜测
And to tell whether a guess is good enough, well, we have to decide something.
为了确定一个猜测是否足够精确 我们需要做一下规定
This is supposed to be a guess for the square root of X,
假设这个是X的平方根的一个猜测
so one possible thing you can do is say,
你可能做的一件事就是
when you take that guess and square it,
当你采用这个猜测并将其平方
do you get something very close to X?
你会得到一个非常接近于X的数
So one way to say that is to say,
而表达这个想法的一种方式是
I square the guess, subtract X from that,
我们用X减去guess的平方
and see if the absolute value of that
并且确认所得结果的绝对值是否
whole thing is less than some small number, which depends on my purposes.
比一个由你规定的很小的数还要小
So there's a complete procedure for how to compute the square root of X.
因此 我们就有了计算X的平方根的一整套过程
Let's look at the structure of that a little bit.
我们再来深入观察一下这个结构
I have the whole thing.
我搞定了整件事
I have the notion of how to compute a square root.
我有一个用于计算X的平方根的记号
That's some kind of module.
这是一种模块
That's some kind of black box.
也是一种黑盒
It's defined in terms of how to try a guess for the square root of X.
它的定义依赖于如何尝试将一个猜测值作为X的平方根
"Try" is defined in terms of, well,
定义try是用来
telling whether something is good enough and telling how to improve something.
确认某数是否足够精确以及如何去改进该数
So good enough.
这是good-enogh?
"Try" is defined in terms of "good enough" and "improve".
try的定义依赖于good-enough?和improve
And let's see what else I fill in.
让我们来看看我填入了些什么
Well, I'll go down this tree.
如果我向下拓展这棵树
"Good enough" was defined in terms of absolute value, and square.
good-enough?的定义依赖于abs和square
And improve was defined in terms of something called averaging
而improve的定义依赖于averaging
and then some other primitive operator.
而其它的都是一些基本运算符
Square root's defined in terms of "try".
平方根的定义依赖于try
"Try" is defined in terms of "good enough" and "improve",
try的定义依赖于good-enough?和improve
but also "try" itself.
甚至依赖于try本身
So "try" is also defined in terms of how to try itself.
因此try也按照它如何应用于自身而进行定义
Well, that may give you some problems.
额 这可能会使你有点糊涂
Your high school geometry teacher probably told you
你的高中几何老师或许告诉过你
that it's naughty to try and define things in terms of themselves,
用一个东西自己去定义自己是很不对的
because it doesn't make sense.
因为这根本行不通
But that's false.
这（种说法）是错的
Sometimes it makes perfect sense to define things in terms of themselves.
有时候用一个东西自己来定义自己非常有意义
And this is the case. And we can look at that.
我们来看看这个例子
We could write down what this means, and say,
假设我问Lisp：2的平方根是多少
suppose I asked Lisp what the square root of 2 is.
我们可以写出它究竟是什么意思
What's the square root of 2 mean?
2的平方根是什么意思
Well, that means I try 1 as a guess for the square root of 2.
意思就是我将用1作为2的平方根的一个猜测
Now I look. I say, gee, is 1 a good enough guess for the square root of 2?
然后我考虑 对于2的平方根来说 1是一个足够好的猜测么
And that depends on the test that "good enough" does.
这取决于good-enough?是如何判断的
And in this case, "good enough" will say,
本例中 good-enough?会说
no, 1 is not a good enough guess for the square root of 2.
不 对于2的平方根来说 1不是一个足够好的猜测
So that will reduce to saying, I have to try an improved--
因此我会继续说 我试试一个改进值
improve 1 as a guess for the square root of 2,
改进猜测值1
and try that as a guess for the square root of 2.
然后将其作为2的平方根的一个猜测
Improving 1 as a guess for the square root of 2
改进猜测值1用作2的平方根
means I average 1 and 2 divided by 1.
也就是说我取1和2/1的平均值
So this is going to be average.
因此我们将取平均数
This piece here will be the average of 1 and the quotient of 2 by 1.
这段代码将会取1和2/1的平均数
That's this piece here.
那么这段代码
And I'm gonna try... And this is 1.5.
我算算 结果是1.5
So this square root of 2 reduces to trying 1 for the square root of 2,
因此这个(sqrt 2)还原到(try 1 2)
which reduces to trying 1.5 as a guess for the square root of 2.
然后还原到(try 1.5 2)
So that makes sense.
因此这行得通
Let's look at the rest of the process.
让我们看下剩下的步骤
If I try 1.5, that reduces.
如果我尝试1.5 则会还原到
1.5 turns out to be not good enough as a guess for the square root of 2.
1.5作为2的平方根的猜测 并不是足够好
So that reduces to trying the average of
然后又还原到
1.5 and 2 divided by 1.5 as a guess for the square root of 2.
(try (average 1.5 (/ 2 1.5)))
That average turns out to be 1.333.
平均值是1.333
So this whole thing reduces to trying 1.333 as a guess for the square root of 2.
然后整个事又还原到(try 1.3333 2)
And then so on.
如此进行下去
That reduces to another called a "good enough", 1.4 something or other.
然后又还原到(good-enough? 1.4)或者其它的
And then it keeps going until the process finally stops
然后这个（步骤）会持续进行到
with something that "good enough" thinks is good enough, which,
good-enough?认为足够好了才停止
in this case, is 1.4142 something or other.
本例中 是1.4242或者其它的东西
So the process makes perfect sense.
因此这个这个过程运行得非常完美
This, by the way, is called a recursive definition.
这种定义方法叫做“递归定义”
And the ability to make recursive definitions is a source of incredible power.
进行递归定义将会给你带来无穷威力
And as you can already see I've hinted at,
之前我已提到过
it's the thing that effectively allows you to do these infinite computations
递归定义可以在不增加任何负担的前提下
that go on until something is true,
仅仅通过调用过程 在达到条件之前
without having any other constricts other than the ability to call a procedure.
完成无限次的计算
Well, let's see, there's one more thing.
还有一点要说明的
Let me show you a variant of this definition of square root here on the slide.
我再在这里给你们演示另外一种平方根的定义方法
Here's sort of the same thing.
这两种方法看起来像是一样的
What I've done here is packaged the definitions of
在这儿 我把improve、good-enough?、try的定义
"improve" and "good enough" and "try" inside "square root".
全都封装在了sqrt里面
So, in effect, what I've done is I've built a square root box.
因此实际上 我们构建了一个平方根盒子
So I've built a box that's the square root procedure that someone can use.
我构建了一个其它人可以使用的平方根盒子
They might put in 36 and get out 6.
它们输入36 然后（盒子）输出6
And then, packaged inside this box
但是 盒子里面封装的过程
are the definitions of "try" and "good enough" and "improve."
就是try、good-enough?和improve的定义
So they're hidden inside this box.
它们都隐藏在盒子里面
And the reason for doing that is that,
这样做是因为
if someone's using this square root,
如果有人正在使用这个平方根
if George is using this square root,
如果George正在使用这个平方根
George probably doesn't care very much that,
George并不会关心
when I implemented square root,
当我在实现平方根时
I had things inside there called "try" and "good enough" and "improve".
我定义了盒子内的那些try、good-enough?和improve过程
And in fact, Harry might have a cube root procedure
事实上 Harry可能会实现一个也具有
that has "try" and "good enough" and "improve".
try、good-enough?和improve的立方根盒子
And in order to not get the whole system confused,
因此 为了不让整个系统变得混乱
it'd be good for Harry to package his internal procedures inside his cube root procedure.
Harry最好把这些内部过程封装在它的立方根过程里
Well, this is called block structure,
这个叫做块结构
this particular way of packaging internals inside of a definition.
这是把东西打包到定义内部的一种方法
And let's go back and look at the slide again.
让我们回过头来再看看
The way to read this kind of procedure is to say, to define "square root",
这种过程的定义读作 定义“sqrt”为
well, inside that definition,
那么 在其内部
I'll have the definition of an "improve" and
我们已有improve的定义
the definition of "good enough" and the definition of "try."
我们已有good-enough?和try的定义
And then, subject to those definitions,
以及这些定义的实体
the way I do square root is to try 1.
我求平方根的定义实体是从1开始尝试
And notice here, I don't have to say 1 as a guess for the square root of X,
注意这里 我不必将X当做参数传递
because since it's all inside the square root,
因为它们都在平方根内部
it sort of has this X known.
它相当于已知这个X了
Let me summarize.
我来总结下
We started out with the idea that
我们从表述指令性知识
what we're going to be doing is expressing imperative knowledge.
开始学习
And in fact, here's a slide that summarizes the way we looked at Lisp.
这张幻灯片总结了一些关于Lisp的知识
We started out by looking at some primitive elements in addition and multiplication,
我们从基本元素如“+”和“*”开始
some predicates for testing whether something is less-than or something's equal.
一些用于测试某物小于或等于的谓词
And in fact, we saw really sneakily in the system we're actually using,
事实上 我们正在使用的系统掩盖了很多细节
these aren't actually primitives, but it doesn't matter.
这些并不是系统的基本元素 但这无所谓
What matters is we're going to use them as if they're primitives.
重要的是我们会把它们当作是基本元素
We're not going to look inside.
我们不会去研究系统的内部
We also have some primitive data and some numbers.
我们也有一些基本数据和一些数
We saw some means of composition, means of combination,
我们学习了合成的手段 组合的手段
the basic one being composing functions and
用运算符和运算对象合成函数
building combinations with operators and operands.
和构建组合式的基本方法
And there were some other things, like COND and "if" and "define".
还有一些像是“COND”、“if”和“define”的东西
But the main thing about "define," in particular,
具体来说 关于“define”的重点则是
was that it was the means of abstraction.
它是一种进行抽象的方法
It was the way that we name things.
它是我们为某物命名的方法
You can also see from this slide not only where we've been,
我们之前提到过  从这里也可以看出来
At some point, we'll have to talk about how you combine primitive data to get compound data,
有时候 我们需要研究如何通过组合基本数据来得到复合数据
and how you abstract data so you can use large globs of data
以及如何抽象数据 使得你可以在一个更大的环境中
as if they were primitive.
将其当作基本数据使用
So that's where we're going.
这也是我们的目的所在
But before we do that, for the next couple of lectures we're going to be talking about,
在我们讨论这个问题之前 下节课我们首先将会讨论
first of all, how it is that you make a link
我们编写的过程与机器内部
between these procedures we write and the processes that happen in the machine.
进程之间的联系
And then, how it is that you start using the power of Lisp
接着 我们将跳出小规模的计算问题
to talk not only about these individual little computations,
来学习如何发挥Lisp的威力
but about general conventional methods of doing things.
来解决更加通用的计算问题
OK, are there any questions?
好了 大家还有什么问题么
AUDIENCE: Yes. If we defined A using parentheses instead of as we did,
学生：在定义A时 如果我们用一个括号将A括起来
what would be the difference?
会与不使用括号不同么？
PROFESSOR: If I wrote this, if I wrote that,
教授：如果我这样写
what I would be doing is defining a procedure named A.
我则会是定义一个过程并命名为A
In this case, a procedure of no arguments, which,
本例中 这个过程没有参数
when I ran it, would give me back 5 times 5.
而当我运行它 则会返回5乘以5
AUDIENCE: Right. I mean, you come up with the same thing,
学生：它们俩完成了相同的事
except for you really got a different--
但本质上是否相同？
PROFESSOR: Right. And the difference would be, in the old one--
教授：好 的确会有不同 之前的那一个
Let me be a little bit clearer here.
我还是在这里写清楚一点吧
Let's call this A, like here.
我们还是把这个叫做A
And pretend here, just for contrast, I wrote,
作为对比 我们假装这里有一个
define D to be the product of 5 and 5.
我定义D为5乘以5
And the difference between those,
这两者的区别则是
let's think about interactions with the Lisp interpreter.
让我们看看它们在Lisp解释器中是怎样的
I could type in A and Lisp would return 25.
我在Lisp中键入A 返回25
I could type in D, if I just typed in D,
如果我仅仅键入D
Lisp would return compound procedure D,
Lisp返回复合过程D
because that's what it is. It's a procedure.
因为D就是一个过程
I could run D. I could say, what's the value of running D?
我可以运行D 我可以问运行D的结果是什么
Here is a combination with no operands.
这是一个没有运算数的组合式
I see there are no operands. I didn't put any after D.
我考虑到它没有运算数 所以我在D后面没有键入任何东西
And it would say, oh, that's 25.
Lisp则会说结果是25
Or I could say, just for completeness, if I typed in, what's the value of running A?
我再说周全一点 如果我键入 A的运行结果是多少
I get an error.
只能得到一个错误
The error would be the same one as over there.
跟这里的错误一样
It'd be the error would say, sorry, 25, which is the value of A,
这个错误是因为 A的值——25
is not an operator that I can apply to something.
并不是我可以应用于某物的运算符
MIT OpenCourseWare
http://ocw.mit.edu
本项目主页
https://github.com/FoOTOo/Learning-SICP